[Music]
hey kids I'm Dave Fisher from
rose-hulman welcome to day one of the
connecting with code camp I want to
start off today by introducing some of
the campers that I have with me and what
I'm going to do is I'm going to switch
to instead of that camera a daddy cam so
you can meet some of our campers
I'll tell actually we'll do them in
birth order so our first first person we
have over here is Neela Neela how old
are you yeah she's four she's a little
too young for the kid so she's going to
play on her iPad now to be just fine and
dandy our next up and the order is
introduce yourself normally a preschool
teacher but you can do this
the next up is kind of have another
person that's great for a target
audience we're gonna introduce yourself
and Keegan who is a perfect gauge for
this he's done a little bit of coding
he's wearing one of our camp t-shirts
from another year he went to the 2018
Boeing for one - he's wearing 2019 and
then our fourth and final camper and one
introduce yourself hi I'm Emily Fisher
I'm 10 years old I'm in fourth grade
fourth grade and so McKinley has done
quite a bit of coding so for her some of
this stuff might be less than what she
needs but that's my that's my team of
campers that I've got here today so
let's go ahead and dive in to what we're
doing hopefully in another video
you learn how to log in to tinker tinker
has a lot of things that you can do by
yourself that's great I do those things
but well we're going to focus on is
things that we're going to do together
called projects so goodness look right
here where it says my projects and what
we're going to do is we're going to make
our first project and so you go and
click on create new project and then
from here like depending on what tab you
got selected you can see that there's a
ton of different types of projects we're
doing what's called block coding right
and we're going to start from scratch so
we want a blank block coding project so
go ahead and click on a blank block
coding project so I'm going to start off
by getting you more familiar with the
tinkerer interface if you happen to know
the scratch interface it's almost
identical right so we're just using
features so you don't have to log into
one place but what we're going to do is
we're going to do something with this
monster just because I always like to
click buttons I go ahead and click the
play button and just kind of see what
happens and you'll notice that they've
given you some code already odd that
makes monster walk back and forth now
sometimes I want my screen a little
bigger I can grab this little button
here and make the screen bigger so this
monster is kind of exciting but after a
while you will get bored watching them
go back and forth let's see how long you
can watch him before you get bored and
what we're going to do today I'm just
going to show you a finished example
real quick so just watch him for a
minute this is a finished example what
we're going to do is we're gonna make
this monster do different things and
what we're gonna make this monster do is
we're gonna make the monster chase your
mouse around right so wherever your
computer mouse goes he'll follow it now
you can work follow along on an iPad if
you want but it's gonna be hard to use a
mouse on an iPad so you have to like
adjust that and his goal is to eat
cupcakes right and every time he eats a
cupcake a couple things happen one thing
that's gonna happen is you'll notice
that there's this variable called food
that's a three right now and as soon as
I get that cupcake it's gonna go down to
two so we're gonna learn about variables
and then if you collect all the cupcakes
it's gonna say you win so that's the
goal that we're trying to make together
today and in doing this we're going to
learn about variables and all the
different things that
doing in Pinker first let's start off by
understanding what we got so what we got
is we got a stage so we have a stage
here you can click on the stage if you
want the stage is perfectly white we're
gonna obviously add a background to our
stage and then we have our actor now his
name is actor which is kind of a
terrible name it's like a human being
called human so let's go ahead and
change his name so go ahead and click in
here where it says actor and you can
actually just backspace over this and
I'm gonna call him monster but you can
call them anything you want if you want
to call your monster Fred or Bob or Dave
I'm a good monster you can do those
things if you'd like now let's look at
some more things with our monster he has
code that's available to him and let's
see if we can figure what some of this
code means so first thing it says is one
starved
so once dark is something that happens
when you hit the start button so when I
hit the start button he does a couple
things first he does something called
set his rotation style - left and right
so he doesn't like go up and down he
just does left and right and that just
has to do with his image and then he
does something forever now this is kind
of funny if I were to walk up to a human
and I would say hey pick up sticks
forever that would be kind of mean I
wouldn't do that to somebody
right but in programming you tell
programs to do things forever all the
time right going all the time and here's
what he has to do forever he has to
animate this walk so you can kind of see
how he's got this animation going on he
has to move ten pixels and he's on an
edge he has to bounce and then so that
it kind of has like a smooth look to it
his speed is controlled by how long he
waits so speed is a function of distance
he moves which is ten pixels and the
time and he things to do it so that
determines how fast he goes if you
wanted to you can make a small change to
him let's say instead of ten pixels you
wanted him to go faster let's have him
go at 30 pixels so what do you think's
gonna happen
he's gonna book it right so now he's
walking super fast back and forth
let's change something else just for fun
what if we were to take out this animate
walk what would happen here's how you
take out code and tinker this is kind of
neat
so there's handles you can kind of see
it's like this gray bar that showed up
on the left and the right if you click
on the left one it selects that code and
all the one below it and if you select
the right one is selects just that one
so kids it's a very like fine motor
skill so some adults might have to help
with this but if you were to take this
right handle and just drag it out of
your code block we'll put it back in a
minute and set it over here if you were
to run it again our program has changed
right and so now you can see he still
moves he still bounces but notice how
he's not animating his walk it's just
like gliding right so that's kind of
what code is is all about so what we're
gonna do
can you make sure we know how to run and
stop our code yeah
so in order to run and stop your code
there's a button down here in the corner
so got a question for one of my campers
at stable here so run you click this
orange play button and then there if you
want to stop I hit the red stop button
and so that's how you run your code or
not and obviously you can usually see
your code running by the stage moving
but also this green outline tells you
for sure that your code is running so
let's start doing some things we could
write this program in any order but I
think what I would like to do first just
for fun is to fix my background so right
now my monster is just on a perfectly
white background so his stage is all
white so I'm gonna see if I can fix that
so to change that you have to click on
the stage and then there's a little gear
over here so you have to click on this
little gear icon the gear icon if used a
lot in computer programs it kinda means
like settings and configuring and things
like that and you'll notice that the
stage has three tabs at the top costumes
say out and advanced so costumes and you
can see that they the stage currently
has none so we want to add one right so
find this button that says
background and now we have to decide
what background to put on now I'm gonna
put that kitchen background that you saw
on the solution but to be honest you can
use any background you want so if you
wanted to do something crazy and
different I don't mind
I'm okay with that but you will have to
pick something that you like so I'm
gonna find that kitchen scene so I think
that there's different categories here
that you can do let's see if I can find
Oh cookie that's where I probably fell
on my kitchenette sure enough here's my
kitchen now I have that that's one of my
backgrounds that's available you'll
notice that in the background here it
actually changed that background and
that's really all we want to do with
this stage so the stage could have code
but it currently has none it's empty and
it has costumes and it's in the costume
that we want now in later videos we'll
do more with the stage but right now
that's plenty that's all we really care
about now we've got our monster
so our monster has some code I kind of
mangled mine because I've taken some
things out and another question from our
[Music]
code I'm gonna help people make
difference okay so we were on stage yeah
cool so you can switch between the stage
code and the actor code that's right
cool all right so let's go ahead and do
some more things with this so the first
thing I want to do is I want him to walk
towards my mouth right so right now he's
just walking directly left and right so
let's see if we can find some code and
put it in there so we're learning about
how this code works you can see that
it's broken up into different categories
the top one is called events and then
there's things with control and a whole
bunch of things we currently care about
motion so see if you can find the
category called motion
so these are different motion commands
that we can have our or actor do our
monster and we want to find one that
says point towards mouse pointer listen
to my words point towards mouse pointer
so there's there's there's two problems
that sometimes happen so one says go to
mouse pointer we don't want that one and
then you have to scroll way down to find
this one point towards mouse pointer now
I'm going to show you what happens if
you grab the wrong one but but I'm going
to add this to my code so before I move
30 pixels I'm gonna aim at the mouse
pointer and then I'm gonna move my 30
pixels that direction not 30 might be
too fast we'll adjust that later
I also liked that walking animation so
I'm gonna put that back in and so those
are the things he does forever
he points towards the mouse pointer does
a little animation moves 30 pixels if
he's on the edge he bounces well we
don't need that anymore so I want rid of
that for my code remember how you can do
that there's a left handle which will
grab it and everything after it and
there's a right handle which will grab
just it we want to grab just it and we
want to take that out of our code now I
don't need that command in my code
anymore at all so instead of setting and
over here to save it for later
I'm just gonna drop it in the trash and
so it's gone so now let's go ahead and
try it again
so now when I run it what should happen
is he should point towards my mouse
pointer and he's currently going 30
pixels we're just kind of fast and he's
trying to get it now an interesting
thing happens if he succeeds in getting
to your mouse pointer he can freaks out
you know because that actually makes
sense because he's going to try to get
it and then he goes past it then he goes
back and we'll try to fix that at some
point today but it is important to
notice that he is going towards my mouse
pointer he doesn't just zoom right there
now your code is hopefully correct but
I'm going to show you what happens if
you did it wrong so don't don't don't
let's say you grabbed that wrong one
let's say you accidentally you weren't
paying good attention
you had goto mouse pointer well go-to
mouse pointer kind of works the same but
you can see that goto he instantly jumps
there right so no matter where the mouse
is he's instantly on top of it so that's
that's an example of a bug so I'm gonna
get rid of that bug and throw it away we
just wanted to point towards the mouse
pointer alright so let's do some more
stuff so one thing that I want to do is
I'm going to teach you about variables
right so there's gonna be a lot of
variables in our code as you saw in the
one before I was collecting cupcakes and
I had five cupcakes so what I want you
to do is I want you to add a variable
and then we'll talk about it so
variables have another area TVs kind of
cut off there but it's called variables
variables are things that like to keep
track of State so like if I'm counting
I've got one two three obviously I've
got a counter and the current state of
the counter is that it's a three let's
go ahead and make a variable so fine
here in orange where it says create
variable and click it and it'll ask you
kind of a complex question it'll ask you
what do you want the variable to be
called
I'm just going to call mine food you can
use uppercase F lowercase F doesn't
matter just so long as you type food now
normally what I need my variables I name
them like really specific I'd be like
you know a number of food remaining but
shorter is better right so food is my
name so type in food and then we're
asked the question you want this for all
actors like does it can it can everybody
see this variable or just this one I'm
gonna choose to say all actors so I
could go into two what that means like
global variables versus other but I want
other people to change it I want my food
to be able to change as well so I'm
gonna say hey make it available for
everybody I'm not going to worry about
any of the other advanced features I'm
just gonna say create so now I have a
variable whenever I run my program it
has some value but the problem is if I
wrong you can't see it right you don't
like it's there but it just doesn't do
anything I want to add something called
a watcher so that we can see this
variable in action and there might still
be a bug with this but we'll see in a
minute so here's what I want to do
inside barriers you're in here click on
food see this orange button that says
add watcher we want to add a watcher now
when you click this button watch over
here to see what happens so I click add
watcher and it created another actor
it created a food watcher I'm going to
click on food watcher down here at the
bottom and you can see that my food
watcher has code in it as well
now there is one bug in this code but
I'll fix it in just a second now my
watcher doesn't move so I'm just going
to put it somewhere to where it's kind
of out of the way you can choose the
corner I'm going to choose the upper
left here you could pick any corner you
wanted and the bug in this by the way is
right now it says property food of
monster but really this should say of
any that's just a bug hopefully tinker
fixes that one but switch that to say
from any and then will will show you
using it so right now if I run my
program it should say food a zero there
oh I forget things all the time let's go
set our very good so made a watcher so
we can see the value but we haven't
given it about you yet let's go back
into the monsters code so this is the
food Watchers codes go back into your
monster and let's set the variable I'm
going to set mine to five to start with
got a question from gonna pause for
problems there's two good options one is
you can
use your mouse to kind of scroll over or
you could zoom out so right here that -
has a zoom out and then you can see it
okay also your code is running right now
so the substring property food of actor
switch it to of any which technically
works better but but not that important
now the other thing that's weird about
yours is where is your food watch rack
the answer is it's right over here
so it kind of got moved over to the Edit
screen so see if you can drag it to the
upper corner mom it was holding the
mouse but the Bowen said that he needed
to take over so see if you can drag that
yeah Bowen knows just what to do
put that right up in the corner great
job though Keegan's got a question so
Keegan says why is there a food walk
here in a food watch for one because he
accidentally clicked watch twice no big
deal so just delete the extra one so
click on the three dots here Keegan and
click on delete and say yes okay yeah
alright so back to where we were this is
how camp really works except for there's
room for like 20 people right and we
pause for questions all the time by the
way when you have questions I know you
can't ask the video but we do have
office hours I'll send the link at that
slant
slash camp page and watch the video
about office hours for that so I want to
set food to five that's my goal so I'm
still in the variables area which is
good and I look down here for this one
that's called set so it says set and
then it's got kind of like an arrow to
zero and what I want to do is the very
first thing in my program I'm going to
drop it I'm on my monster I'm going to
drop it right here I'm going to say set
food to five
and now when I run it what should happen
is it should say food and spas
now variables don't have to be visible
on the screen oftentimes variables in
programmer just hidden they're inside
your computer somewhere but because
we're learning about variables we do
want to put a watcher on art appear so
that we can see it right cool campers
you doing good yep you totally could so
the question is could you start it at
zero and count up or do you have to
start at five we can now I choose to do
a countdown so I'm going to start five
and then get last as I go now in order
in order to actually get this variable
to count down we're going to need other
actors I'm going to use cupcakes but you
can use any food item you'd like I'm
gonna use cupcakes and when I collect
those cupcakes the counter is gonna get
lower and lower so campers we all ready
to add a new actor all right so click on
add actor now there's different ways you
can add actors you can draw an actor
from scratch we'll do that sometime you
can have it be a character builder which
is kind of like an advanced thing like
my monster or you can just use their
media library which is some of their
safe things that's what we're gonna do
so we're gonna say media library we use
a couple of those different things but
media libraries will what now
and now what we want to do is we want
our monster to collect something I'm
going to use cupcakes but you can use
whatever you'd like
so cupcakes are probably in the cooking
area and so I'm going to look around for
a delicious food in here if you wanted
to use cakes or maybe your monster likes
cheese you could do whatever you want
but I'm going to do a cupcake because I
love cupcakes so I'm gonna click on this
cupcake right here and you'll see that
that did a couple of things I'm curious
what I can't
Fix Keegan picked a bomb so he's gonna
collect bombs bowen picked Oh a big
birthday cake that looks yummy both and
McKinley picked a coin so she's gonna
collect coins so everybody can do their
own thing to make it their game so
whatever I add this actor a couple of
things happen the first thing you'll
notice is that there's a giant cupcake
on my screen that's a little big like
this monster can only handle so much
cupcake that's a little bit yeah so it
depends on your actor that you added
whether it's big or tiny so they've all
said that there's a super tiny so they
might need to make theirs a little
bigger but mine came in super big and
you need to resize it so that it's a
reasonable size so I'm gonna make mine
maybe this big and I'm just gonna put it
somewhere in my scene that kind of makes
sense so I'm gonna set my cupcake all
right on the counter top and so now I've
got a cupcake up there now the cupcake
can have code you can see it's currently
empty
he can have code and he can up things
that he does what the cupcake is gonna
do is the cupcake is gonna watch if the
monster hits him and then if the monster
does hit him he's going to hide and
change the variable right so I make
sense let's go ahead and write some code
for the cupcake now eventually we're
gonna have five but don't duplicate it
yet wait till we finish it and then
duplicate it then you only have to write
that code once instead of five times so
that makes sense
all right cupcake code the first thing
you need for code is an event should go
to the events tab
the most common event is called on start
so go ahead and drag that over if you
happen to be familiar with scratch this
is similar to the on green flag clicked
but in Tinker it's called it's called on
starter and so now we're gonna have code
that's inside this cupcake now I'm going
to tell the cupcake to do something
forever so just like before
I go to control so it's in a different
category
I find the command called forever I'm
going to say hey cupcake do this forever
I really want to go tell people to do
things forever right but I'll resist the
urge and what the cupcake is going to do
forever is he's going to always check am
i touching the monster am i touching the
monster am i touching the monster and if
he is then he's going to do something so
inside of this forever loop we want him
to check am i touching the monster
that's called an if-statement so an if
statement is also in control so you can
just kind of drag it over and what he
says is if false then do something
that's just a placeholder that word
false we're gonna fix that right because
we wanted to say if I'm touching the
monster then do stuff so see that shape
for the word false it's kind of like a
little hexagon right go to a new
category called sensing and we're gonna
look for that same shape so sensing you
can see it's color-coordinated and you
can see that there's a lot of things
that are that shape so we can put things
in there so there's one yep I'm touching
the mouse pointer I can put that in
there
if I'm touching a clone of the mouse
pointer what does that even mean if I'm
touching some color and so the question
is we wanted one that said if I'm
touching the monster do something but is
not on there turns out that this command
right here touching mouse pointer you
can change the word Mouse corner to
something different
so take touching mouse pointer which is
that correct shape and get it to drop in
here by the way you get better at
dropping things in but you can kind of
see when it's gonna work because the the
box changes to kind of grow until let it
fit in here right and you can see that
it actually uses kind of the left edge
for deciding when it's in there not
where your mouse is out so if I'm
touching the mouse pointer is not what I
want but if I click on the word mouse
pointer then I can change it to what I
want right so I want to change it to say
if I'm touching the monster and that's
the idea of block based languages
kind of human readable by the way we
really are making javascript is the
language we're really using under the
hood we won't go into this but if you
click on this button it'll show you the
JavaScript code and then I'm going to
quickly get out of it but the neat thing
is is it's the exact same as what
professional developers use it's just
with blocks it's easier for people that
aren't as good at typing right alright
so if I'm touching the monster then I
want to do a couple of things one is I
want to hide right so I want to want to
Duck and Cover
hide is something you see so that sim
looks so fine looks and we've got to
find the word hide so there's a bunch of
commands inside looks where is high
whereas high got there it is way down at
the bottom so probably easiest to scroll
to the very bottom and look from the
bottom find hobby so I went to hide and
then in addition to hiding I also want
to decrement the counter just by one
right so I've got hide so now I want to
go there's another command that I know
we're going to need to add so I'm just
going to do while I'm here if you hide
now then you probably ought to show at
some other time let's go ahead and put
this at the very top of our code I was
gonna let that be a bug that we figured
out later but just so easy to add now so
when the program starts show me just in
case I was hidden before and then
forever check for the monster and if I'm
touching the monster that I hide that
makes sense
all right so show and hide are both in
there now no bugs that we'll have to
find later let's go change that variable
so variables have a category for
variables and what we want to do is we
want to change the variable so before we
set the variable which that just like
set it to five but now we want to change
it by one so take this change by one and
put it underneath hide now the variable
that we want to change is food so say
hey change
by one now if we run it then what should
happen is it should be chasing my mouse
around and if he gets that you can see
that it changed the variable food and it
made it go from five to six so it worked
but it didn't work perfectly right
what should we change this value to
instead of one what should it be all
right I can tell by looking at my
audience that I've got some questions so
that so the the dr. Fisher came I think
I felt I did dad I came before the dr.
Fisher cam is gonna go walking around
but it should change from five down to
four if you put it into negative one so
this cupcake I think is in pretty good
shape I want five of them right so I'm
gonna duplicate it five times now when
you get into coding and you're an adult
there are more elegant ways to do things
but because we're young we're just gonna
duplicate it right and so right now I've
got two cupcakes now this will happen to
you so I'm just gonna show it to you if
I hit stop my cupcakes are gone because
they're hidden I'm what I do to bring
them back side is hit play and then stop
and then another right so I've got two
cupcakes and now I'm hit duplicate again
now I've got three duplicate again I got
four duplicate again now I got five now
I'm going to position them in my room
such that they're kind of like fun and
interesting places and I'm going to
position my monster such that he doesn't
start like right on top of them now this
is not the world's most amazing game
it's not that exciting to play over and
over again but there's concepts that
we're going to build on throughout the
week to do interesting things so now I
have five cupcakes which is great and if
I play my game I should be able to watch
my variable count down
because that because all my cupcakes are
countdowns it should count down by
negative one every time it touches a
cupcake yeah all the way to zero so I'm
chasing my mouse around and now whenever
he gets on the mouse he kind of freaks
out a little bit that's that's a feature
for now we can show you how to fix that
later but whenever I collect a cupcake
it drops to four now three now two now 1
and then finally 0 now you'll notice
that nothing really happened when I got
to 0 just all the cupcakes were gone so
your game only does what you tell it to
do so mine is supposed to say you win
right but it doesn't do that yet that's
because you ever written it yet right so
that's very common whenever you write
things so I hit stop there and all my
cupcakes are gone so I'm gonna do this
trick again where I hit play and then
stop just to bring them all back that's
just I like to see them that's just a
personal preference all right so let's
go ahead and have the have the monster
say you win when you win right all right
so I want the Monster to say it so I've
got to go to the monster's code and in
the monster you can see what he's doing
right now he's pointing towards the
mouse pointer he's animating he's moving
his 30 pixels he's waiting a little bit
which determines his speed we also want
to check to see if the variable is zero
anytime you want to check something
that's an if statement so I get pretty
used to making F favorites so good of
control the very first thing in control
is an if statement I'm just going to put
it at the bottom of my loop it doesn't
matter where it happens in the loop it
could be anywhere in there well what I
want to do is I'm going to check if my
variable is equal to something right in
my case 0 so I want to say is my
variable equal to 0 what I want to do is
I want to find another hexagon that can
help me do that and it's in operators so
I'm looking for the equals operator
you can see that there's a couple
operators this one has kind of like a
circle of edge so you know it can't be
any of those more circle edges down here
it says boolean as the category and I'm
looking for a command that has an equal
symbol it looks like it's the second one
down I in the boolean area so does this
equal this and it's a diamond so you
know that it can go into that diamond
box drop it right in there now I want to
check my variable against some number so
I have to go to variables this getting
good at bouncing around categories is a
very important skill so so make sure you
practice it and I want to check my
variable I have to scroll up some and
here's my variable food so I take food
and I drop it into one side of this
equals test and I say if food equals and
not have to pick my number I am starting
at five and I'm counting down and so
when I get to zero that means you win if
you're counting up you'll have to change
your number is appropriate for what you
want to do right so you can do whatever
you want to do but when I get to zero
I win now I'm gonna say you win just be
a like a dialog box and a dialog box is
something you can see so the category
we're looking for is looks so go down
the whoops now what we want to do is we
want to say you win for some number of
seconds so I just kind of scroll down
through here for them there's a category
called speech bubbles there's a couple
of different speech bubbles you can see
there's these big scary two that have
lots and lots of options on them they're
my favorites and then there's the really
simple ones down here like say hello for
two seconds I like simple but I don't
like the font size of it so I'm going to
use the big scary box so I'm going to
use this very top them there looks like
it has a bazillion options and I'm gonna
drop it in here it
I got the wrong one don't grab the top
one grab-grab down grab the top of I
said grab the top one but then I grabbed
the second one so we want say hello for
two seconds you notice that the second
one didn't have to for two seconds right
now instead of saying hello type in some
different message you can say you win or
something like that or whatever your
monster name say whatever you want right
so shows like bones bones got a crazy
idea
Bolin what is your monster gonna say you
win yum yum and mom's gonna help type it
for him because there's no reason to
make them tight to the you win yum yum
message and now by default it uses a
really tiny font it uses 18 instead of
an 18 I'm gonna make it a bigger number
I'm gonna make it be 48 now that 18 you
can switch it to whatever you want but I
happen to know that 18 is tiny so I'm
gonna switch it to 48 also being a big
nerd it's currently going to show up as
a bottom message box I don't want that I
want it to be like a speech bubble right
so you can use a rectangular speech
bubble or a rounded speech bubble
doesn't matter right I'm just going to
pick pick what you want there and you
can also change the colors but I'm not
going to go into the colors right so
let's go ahead and see if this works
so now food is five and he's following
my mouse so now food is for food is
three to one and then when I hit this
last one it should say you win and it
works now there is a minor problem it's
not a big problem but my game is still
playing and my game is still saying you
win every two seconds right so the game
is like still going right so you've won
the game the game is over
but the games still going how do we make
the game stop
yeah there's got to be some command for
stop right so our last bit of code is we
want the game to stop now one way to
stop it is to hit the stop button by the
way I like to bring my my cupcakes back
so I hit play and stop just to bring
them back personal choice now if I want
the game to stop that is a control type
of thing and so it must be a command
that's in the control area stop is the
very very bottom one so scroll to the
very very bottom of control and finally
this stop all commands now I'm going to
show you where it goes but then I'm
gonna do it wrong intentionally right
here's where it goes it goes just below
saying you win right so it goes right
there so you put yours right there right
so it's gonna say you win for two
seconds and then it's just gonna stop
the program right so it goes immediately
after the textbox stop all right you put
it there I'm gonna show you a bug this
is an annoying bug let's say that I
wasn't paying good attention let's say
that I put it right here and you're like
well that looks like it's the same place
it's not alright so you can see that
it's not because the if statement does
these things and stop is not inside of
it that's bad right let's see what
happens with that bad code so here's
what happens I hit play and my game
stops right away well why did that
happen try again but it's really
annoying right so this is a bug now if
tinker does try to help you with bugs
there's this little bug symbol up here
you can try to see what's going on and
you hit this bug symbol and what it does
is it'll try to like let you see what's
happening it's got a help message in
here which you should definitely read
right what I'm gonna do is I'm going to
hit play
and you can see that goes through my
code and it shows me what all is
happening with the debugger you kind of
see it was fast there right and you can
see that why
is every time through my Luke I mean
always hit stop all so that's why it's
above right bugs were made popular by
grace after long ago but I've got that
command in the wrong spot and so I've
used the debugger there and it showed me
with that little bug symbol what was
wrong and that bug symbol can sometimes
be useful sometimes not I did that but
let's go ahead and fix mine and I want
to move it up to where it's inside of
the F statement so it only stops when
that F statement screwed so now I can go
around and collect cupcakes and it'll
say you win and then after you've won it
just stops the game right Bolan already
did is good job either
alright so that was actually the end of
the required thing I'm going to show you
some extra features that you could add
if you wanted but that's the end of the
required thing and one thing that we I
did a bad job of is we haven't saved
yeah right I don't know how much you
know about coding but I'll say that
saving is important and so before we say
that we should also give it a name I'm
gonna name mine monster feast so I just
click up there I decide what to what to
call you can also call it like coding
camp day one things like that and then I
can click on the button save or I can
also click on this down arrow any time
you make a project you can save it just
for you or you could save it and publish
it to the community I actually don't
care which one you do but I tend to
publish a lot of things through the
community just because it's fun and you
can do whatever you want so example from
day one of camp and the nice thing about
published projects is then other people
can see them so like other people in our
class can see your projects so I like to
publish mine just just so that I can see
now there's a couple extra features if
you would like to add them these are not
required at all the extra features if
you'd like to add them is I made mine
still have another variable this is
optional you don't have to do it while
they're variable to speed
notice how we slow right now so I have
another variable called speed and it
starts at 10 and then every time I
collect a cupcake I changes by 10 so it
gets 10 bigger and you can see that I
use my speed variable right here so I
say move speed pixels and so now every
time I collect a cupcake you know I
could go look at their code but it's
gonna make speed 10 bigger I chose not
to put a washer on it it's just a
variable that's just in my computer
somewhere and then when I win it stops
the game another feature that I added
which you do not have to add is that I
made it to where he gets to the mouse
he stops so instead of freaking out he
just stops when he gets there I don't
care if you do that one or not but the
way you do it is the move you wrap that
inside of an if statement and you only
move if you're not touching the mouse
pointer so if you're not touching the
mouse pointer then move but if you are
touching the mouse printer stop that is
an extra in something you don't have to
do at all alright so that is the the end
of this video how did my how do my
campers do Bowen did you make a finish
game out of yours click on that alright
try to collect your cakes bow one k23
all the moment of truth boom boom you
win
yum yum hey Bowen nicely done McKinley
did you make a finish game all right
let's see McKinley so call today so
she's collecting coins and then when she
gets the last one you win and her game
stops alright thank you much for calling
there should be more videos coming soon
and more phonics for things you can do
see you next time bye
[Music]